when um man that's
distracting
distracting okay I just won't share
screen it's what's causing
it where I was getting at was okay so on
the one hand we we have this
discretization and this continuity and
on the other hand uh we can we have this
embedding of the discreetness within the
continuity or the continuity uh within
the
discreetness um or there's like
nestedness right where you like you have
like discreetness continuity continuity
within the continuity and so on and so
forth but
also uh while we have the prioritization
of what's Happening there's also kind of
like a tuning aspect right like a tune
like there's tuning me mechanics
happening right like when you think of
stuff like hyperplanes and or hyper
parameterization um I think a beautiful
paper to look at um is biological
cognition by uh I think is hubner and
schulen and um they bring up this term
called
heterarchical processing right and
heterarchical has to do with like
selective tuning or you think of like a
like you're an audio engineer and you're
mixing you have a you have a mixing
board and you're trying to get the right
trying to mix the channels and all that
together the right way like this tuning
or this adaptive tuning rather but it's
like there's like a mix of there's
layers of the hierarchical and then n
tuning happening right so so it's not
even though I would argue it's mostly
hierarchical you still have this tuning
happening right you still have this sort
of like this degrees of tuning happening
but I'm not sure if that I like I'm I
already am like about I'm on chapter
five right now TR it's chapter four but
I'm not sure if the book really
addresses like this hyper
parameterization issue but I guess you
can kind of go over that if you can yeah
yeah yeah that's um I think that's a
really interesting point too so
whenever I don't want to find the the
figure I don't have it top of mine but
it's I'm it's in the second half of the
book and it might be in the section of
learning but what are your what
everything you're saying about like
tuning and
hyperparameters th those are absolutely
like those are compon like directly
components not just figuratively and in
active inference models and so what what
you can have is like like I mentioned
Precision earlier that came up at the
end of the the chapter this chapter um
but you can actually like Precision can
be modulated such that it impacts the
rest of the model once you have a
hierarchical model it's like it's not
just you know every once in a while
something happens here but most of the
time it's over here it's like the whole
model is integrated right and so you do
have this really strong constant
interplay
um between the different layers um so so
that that that hopefully at least figure
figuratively gives you some sense of
like the the way you describe like a
continuous and the discret the discreet
and the continuous it's like well as far
as like coding a simulation you do have
to more clearly Define one versus the
other at least at each layer um but then
that said they're so tightly integrated
it's as if you know the discret is
impacting the The Continuous in given
moment and vice versa so that's there
and then somewhere in the in the in the
textbook there's um there's another
figure showing the PDP we were looking
at earlier but it also adds on
hyperparameters and those very
hyperparameters are what can be adjusted
or tuned and they relate to Precision uh
for example you could have agent learn
its a matrix meaning the the likelihood
Matrix which figures in this chapter and
so they might learn to you know let's
say we we have our Mouse in the t- Maze
the agent right let's say they
repeatedly go through the maze over and
over and through trial and error um end
up learning that the stimulus is always
on the left let's say we're we're the
experimenters we to choose that let's
say the stimulus is is always on the
left for an agent who's who's who who
who undertakes or engages in learning um
it's not only going to try and minimize
its free
energy uh it's variational free energy
but it'll actually start to modify and
change its beliefs within that a matrix
to where it'll start to associate the
cheese or the attractive stimulus with
the location left in the Maze right it's
belief about that um and so that's
that's how that plays in but kind of
tweaking to the models and so on so we
have we have learning they H something
like hyper parameters here in the case
of
precisions U are directly implicated so
all that all that is here but that's a
really
interesting paper that you you brought
up um I almost feel like other folks uh
other members of The Institute might
find some interest in that um
found something heterarchical control
mechanisms in biology does that sound
right yeah
um if there's like any resources you
have to suggest for me to look into i'
would love to take a look at it because
I haven't really found something other
than that one paper I
mentioned it's biological bi cognition
um it's I think it's published through
Cambridge um
yeah it's the one through uh when you
look it up biological cognition it's the
Cambridge
article um it's paywalled but uh I was
able to get a copy of
it nice but uh yeah I I hate when when
like really nice papers are pay walled
it's like H it's such a crime you know
it's anyway yeah I mean I'm always
looking for more papers that talk about
this hyper mization stuff um because I
feel like there's just not enough out
there explaining that there's so much
stuff talking about hierarchy and like
embedding things in hierarchies and even
though I would say like the hyper
parameterization requires hierarchical
stuff in order to be effective it it's
still not
hierarchical in its nature but um yeah I
I you know definitely throw it at me I'm
I'm Catman do on Discord so if you want
to if you DM me that those resources if
you find them or even share it in one of
the channels I'll definitely I'm I'm
constantly eyeballing what's shared on
server so yeah in uh for the
relationship between discreet and
continuous in the machine learning
Paradigm what they actually use is a
mechanism called clip uh which is simply
going to take the energy relationship
between this categorical and this
discreet thing and then just throw it in
whatever's easier which happens to be uh
language in our case for uh large
language models so what you do is you
find the most straightforward
abstraction layer uh this is going to be
naturally hierarchical if we're talking
about deep learning in this specific
example uh you create that abstraction
layer and then you just keep it
consistent through the entire thing uh
two other things that might be related
to what you're talking about is
anthropics most recent paper uh which I
forgotten the name of I'll have to find
it but
they essentially talk about not
hyperparameters but the expectation of
the actual state that you're putting
into it which uh they Define as a
feature a feature is going to be deeply
related to what we consider to be a
concept like a dog or a cat or something
like that and being able to take these
Concepts which kind of create these
little bubbles that you can create a
context around there is some situation
that it's talking about which has some
set of features which are going to be
activated how much you activate these
certain features are going to be deeply
related to what you're saying about
these
hyperparameters so deciding which hyper
parameters to use is going to be found
right now in machine learning through
the creation of do we make this feature
really big do we shut these features
down to be really small and that's going
to be how we control how these
hierarchical mechanisms are actually
going
to consistently be able to produce the
results that we're looking for one other
slightly related thing is of the
application of going through the network
and having a kind of a meta Network
decide what inside of the network to
actually
create this is going to be a very recent
paper called uh it gets into a bit of
the weeds but it's a mixture of a
million experts which essentially takes
the entire hierarchical network that
we're going to be dealing with and all
of the variables are going to be encoded
into these on layer MLPs these one layer
fully connected networks and from there
we're going to find a way to create a
meta Network which decides which ones to
turn on and these ones that I'm talking
about are going to be analogous to
hyperparameters and it's taking a large
Network which again talks about the
context that you're speaking of and
being able to decide which ones are
important which facts are important
inside of what we're talking about and
only turning those on which I think is
deeply analogous to the hyper thing but
that does lead me to a question of
whenever we're talking about hierarchies
in the active inference
domain how much does it matter you guys
were talking about system one earlier
how much does it matter with respect to
continuous or discret variables once you
get past the system one level of the
direct input from the external
environment that you're trying to
understand do you guys think that once
you enter into a hierarchy it's all just
abstracted away or do you guys think
that the discreetness or the
continuousness of the actual input is
going to have really deep ramifications
as you go down the
line I'm sorry if that was a lot great
great comment we'll each just give a
short closing thoughts in these last
minutes I mean shortest answer it simply
100% dictates it it's like asking about
a
transistor how would it matter what the
composition of the metal is or how would
it matter what the size of the plate or
how closely these elements are it's like
it simply determines it so then there
there might be some situations where you
could discretize a continuous and get
this or that performance retention or or
the other way around but that's kind of
the fun is the textbook is just showing
us those fundamental motives and uh Toby
SMI in the structured active inference
live stream earlier today showed that in
a in a far more comprehensive way than
the Markov blanket formalism with the
broader applied category theory for
interfaces so it's like all about how
it's specified like a physical
transistor or Linux kernel
deployment I also um this is this I
don't know if this is a little too
simple relative to to what we were all
just discussing but I did drop a a link
to one paper uh into the chat there and
that is um deep active inference and
scene construction and just given we
have such little time left I just wanted
to drop something there is U what with
as a kind of combination of things we're
talking about including hierarchical
modeling um and here the idea of like
looking at particular features that when
combined maybe allows for let's say
class ification or categorization of uh
in this case the paper I shared like a
visual stimuli it's rather interesting
they put together so a two- layer model
where um it's like a sod experiment so
it's like uh someone is viewing a 2 by
two grid and then they make inferences
based on particular things that they see
um in each of the um uh coordinates of
that 2 by two grid and then they uh from
there have to infer certain aspects of
what's going on in each of those two
grids and then that gets pushed up to a
higher discrete level that allows them
to uh to make an inference as to how
they should categorize the entire uh
scene the entire 2 by two grid like what
is going on in there it's based on a
previous experiment that's very similar
but uh it would just be um it it's it's
a way to kind of
simplify uh a lot of the principles
we're sort of talking about here uh but
also being able to see something like
trying trying to theorize like how does
scene construction happen if you look at
a
broader uh expanse and you're trying to
figure out like infer a belief about
what is going on there well your eyes
are limited and so they can only look at
certain points so how do you start to
construct represent a belief about what
the overall scene is based on particular
features that you look at and you have
to make inferences about those
individual features in the first place
so you know for me to look at a you know
an overview of like a street and I don't
know exactly where you know that is in
the city I have to look at different
parts of the overall image I have to
infer oh that's a particular sign that's
particular building so on eventually to
the higher order inference of where am I
what what is this location so I just
thought that one would be interesting um
I'll try to add other things that that
maybe come to mind uh in the Cota um and
uh yeah really really interesting talk
today so thanks
everyone thank you fellows see you yeah
thank you both so much bye guys bye